קמ"ד Kuf-Mem-Daled is דף, daf, we pick up on the bottom of
קמ"ג עמוד ב'. Kuf-Mem-Gimmel Amud-Bet. We're still talking about ברית מילה Brit
Milah on שבת, Shabbat, and we turn to an issue which has
become quite a matter of controversy these days, מציצה. metzitzah. Eight lines
from the bottom, last word on the line, מוצצין. motzitzin. So it
says the following: מוצצין. motzitzin. So the משנה Mishna says you do
the, you cut the skin, you peel away the membrane, and then
it says you do מציצה, metzitzah, you suck out the blood from
the wound, and then it talks about ways of medically treating the
wound. So interestingly, מציצה metzitzah is situated right at the crossroads, right
between the first part of the משנה Mishna where it talks about
the acts of the מילה milah and the second part of the
משנה Mishna which talk about the medical treatment relating to issues of
סכנה. sakana. So let's see where the גמרא Gemara places it. So
אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, says רב פפא, Rav Papa, like
again eight lines from the bottom, beginning of a line or seven
lines, אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa: האי אומנא, Hai umna, this
מוהל, mohel, דלא מייץ, delo mayitz, who does not do מציצה, metzitzah,
who does not suck out the wound, סכנה הוא, sakana hu, he
is endangering the infant,
ועברינא ליה, ve-abrinah lei, and we therefore, we, we, you
know, kick him out of his post. We do not allow him
to continue being a מוהל. mohel. So the גמרא Gemara says so
his חידוש hiddush has two parts. Number one is if somebody's being
irresponsible, we kick them out of their job, specifically irresponsible about issues
related to the health, and number two, that this is fundamentally a
health issue, not a מצוה mitzvah issue. So the גמרא Gemara says
פשיטא, pshita, this is obvious, מדקמחלי עלה שבתא, mi de-kamichaleli alei shabata,
since you're מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat for it because you suck it
out and that's making a חבורה, habura, סכנה הוא, sakana hu, obviously
it must be a risk to life. No, the גמרא Gemara says
מהו דתימא, mah d'teima, I might have thought האי דמא מפקד פקיד,
hai dama nifkad pakid, it's not a real סכנה, sakana, a risk
not to do it. A risk not to do it, exactly. So
I might have thought that the blood in the wound is sort
of is stored up, meaning it's only a violation of שבת Shabbat
if you break essentially, thank you, a blood vessel and you free
the wound and you sort of and you make blood come out.
But let's say for example you had some type of a like
a of a
growth on your skin that had blood like you know like that
was just inside of it, right? So it's not in any blood
vessel, it's just essentially there like in a bag, in a sack,
okay, and you opened it up. That would not be חבורה. habura.
חבורה habura is only releasing it from a blood vessel. So the
גמרא Gemara said I might have thought this wasn't real חילול שבת,
hilul Shabbat, that maybe the blood there is like stored and it's
not really in the blood vessel and therefore it's not real חילול
שבת. hilul Shabbat. קא משמע לן חבובי מיחבר. kamashmalan hibubi mikhbar. So
you see that no, the blood actually is connected, it's in the
blood vessel and you're removing it from it, and it's real חילול
שבת, hilul Shabbat, and nevertheless you're allowed to do it because of
a סכנה. sakana. So the גמרא Gemara says ודומיא דאספלנית וכמון, vedumiya
de-isplanit ve-kammon, וגמר, ve-gamar, and I can
and I learn that this is part of a סכנה sakana issue
from the fact that it is in the same category as the
אספלנית isplanit and כמון. kammon. מה אספלנית וכמון, mah isplanit ve-kammon, the
same way in the משנה Mishna the אספלנית isplanit and כמון, kammon,
דאי לא עבדי סכנה הוא, d'ilo abdi sakana hu, that that's clearly
that that's a medical issue and if you're and you're allowed to
violate שבת Shabbat and if not it's a סכנה, sakana, אף הכא
נמי דלא עביד סכנה הוא, af hachami delo abdi sakana hu, here
too if you don't do it, it is a סכנה. sakana. That
is all the גמרא Gemara has to say about
מציצה. metzitzah. So if you were wondering where the entire מציצה metzitzah
issue comes from, it's
whatever it is, it's a lot of stuff that grows up post
the גמרא Gemara that gives a lot of sort of you know
Kabbalistic or weight to the act of מציצה metzitzah or maybe specifically
a focus on blood. We'll talk about that a little later today
that you know the idea of blood being an important part of
the act of מילה milah is not at all so clear. You
know the emphasis of the מילה milah is cutting away the skin,
the משנה Mishna we just read really didn't mention anything about blood.
Oh yeah, okay, but that's not in the פסוקים, psukim, that's in
the מדרש. Midrash. So we'll talk about that, okay, but in terms
of the מעשה מצוה ma'aseh mitzvah of מילה milah and so on.
But anyway in the גמרא Gemara it's very clear that it's all
about a health issue. So the fact that right now it's a
big concern because it causes health real health danger is of course
very sadly ironic and you understand
why
you know an argument could be made even not to do it
at all if there's other ways of addressing whatever health concerns there
are about an untreated wound. I mean in the day people would
like suck out wounds in order to get out like in order
I mean certainly get out venom, but also wouldn't you do it
like infection or something? No, no reason to suck out a wound
for any particular purpose.
No, you'd lance it open and treat it with something.
Aha, unless it's
if it's dirty, right, then you would clean it.
That's what I mean.
But you'd want the blood to flow free, right? Okay. So there
could be certain issues but you know again, the point is that
if you were if you did not have a lot of this
baggage, oh that's a bad word, but anyway you know a lot
of this tradition or you know weight around it that's not in
the גמרא, Gemara, you would have treated this like many of the
other things we've been reading for the past few months about health
issues in the גמרא Gemara that you assess those. health issues based
on current medical knowledge and you move on. And even if you
want to do מציצה, metzitzah, the emphasis of מציצה בפה metzitzah b'peh
and so on, so it's quite ironic about how big of an
issue this מציצה metzitzah thing has become nowadays.
They're making
an assumption.
Yeah, sure. They're also assuming that you have a bandage and cumin.
Are the same מוהלים mohalim that are crazy מחמיר machmir about מציצה
בפה metzitzah b'peh making sure that they have cumin that they treat
the... No, not that I know of. No, no, it's not because...
No, מציצה metzitzah has become ritualistic, whereas in the גמרא, Gemara, it
was very much just about a medical treatment. Yes, so was cumin
and a bandage. It doesn't mean that it's absolutely required. I've never
seen cumin and a bandage, I've seen cumin... No, anyway. No, no,
no, no. All
right, so now we continue. That's what you need to know about
מציצה. metzitzah. Now we continue. ונותנין עליה אספלנית, venotnin aleha isplanit, you
put on it a bandage. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אמרה לי
אם, amra li em, my mother said to me... אביי Abaye actually
mother had died and he was raised by his nursemaid. So when
he says אמרה לי אם, amra li em, he refers to his
nursemaid. Also very often he quotes his nursemaid saying his mother in
the name like with this like wisdom of medical wisdom or treating
of infants wisdom relating to sicknesses and so on. So here is
what he says. אמרה לי אם, amra li em, by the way
some people say, I think this might just be apocryphal, but anyway,
some people say because אביי's Abaye mother had died that the word
אביי Abaye is an acronym for
אשר בך ירוחם יתום. Asher becha yerucham yatom. That's a very sweet
idea, I don't know if it's true. But that God gives compassion
to the orphan. Anyway, so אביי Abaye said, אמרה לי אם, amra
li em, my mother, i.e., my nursemaid said to me, אספלניתא דכולהון,
isplanita dekulaun, this sort of bandage, not bandage, but you know like
a poultice, a poultice for דכולהון כיבי dekulaun kivi of
all types of aches, שב מיני תרבא shav minei tarba seven types
of fat, וחד קירא vechad kira and one unit of type רש"י
Rashi says that that's wax. רבא אמר, Rava amar, so that's how
you make a poultice that will help for all things. רבא אמר,
Rava amar, רבא Rava says, קירא וכלבא רישנא, kira vekalva rishana, it's
wax and this כלבא רישנא kalva rishana which רש"י Rashi says is
a type of a tree sap.
דרש רבא במחוזא, darsha Rava beMechuza, so רבא Rava sort of expounded
this in מחוזא Mechuza which was רבא's Rava city. He told everybody
here's a great way you can get a bandage that will heal
all types of things. וקרעו בני מניומי אסיא למאניהו, vekarinu bnei Minyomi
asya lemanaihu, so the sons of מניומי Minyomi the doctor all rent
their garments because he gave away a trade secret and now they
were going to be out of business. So אמר להו, amar lehu,
so רבא Rava said to them, שבקי לכו חדא, shavti lakhu chada,
I left you over one trade secret, דאמר שמואל, de'amar Shmuel, because
שמואל Shmuel says, האי מאן דמשי אפיה ולא נגיב טובה, hai man
demashi appei velo nagiv tuva, if a person washes his face and
doesn't dry it well, נכתרו ליה חספניתא, naktaru leh chaspanita, so basically
his face will become like a you know will like crack will
develop
like you know cracks in whatever like you know what's the word
anyway yeah not sores but you know it's like it's like it'll
become
like crusty and yeah yeah fissures or whatever anyway so מאי תקנתיה,
mai takantei, so what do you do if this happens? So and
this is the secret which he says I didn't tell everybody else.
למשי טובה במיא דסילקא, limshi tuva bemaiya desilka, you should wash well
in beet water. So that's the secret I didn't reveal. Okay, moving
on. לא שחק מערב שבת, lo shachak me'erev Shabbat, now if you
did not grind the cumin from ערב שבת, erev Shabbat, you can
do it on שבת Shabbat but you do it with your teeth.
Interesting it asks you to do it with a שינוי shinuy even
though presumably this is a סכנת נפשות. sakanat nefashot. I mentioned the
other day that we do find שינוי shinuy mentioned by ברית מילה
beris milah for the health issues and by a woman who gave
childbirth and some of that might be because we put them in
the category of פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh even without knowing the specifics
of their case. So because we sort of apply broadly this
category, we do sort of try to push a little bit for
a שינוי. shinuy. Whereas in a case where there's a real immediate
an obvious פיקוח נפש, pikuach nefesh, we would not be making these
types
of preferences of pushes. So anyway, so that's in terms of grinding
the cumin. So it says תנו רבנן, tano rabanan, we taught, דברים
שאין עושים למילה בשבת עושים לה ביום טוב. devarim she'ein osim lemillah
beShabbat osim lah beYom Tov. Things we don't let you do for
ברית מילה beris milah on שבת Shabbat directly, only indirectly or with
a שינוי, shinuy, we allow you to do on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. שוחקין לה כמון, shochin lah kamon, for example you can directly
grind the cumin on יום טוב Yom Tov because יום טוב Yom
Tov you can do things for food, so you could even grind
spices, and therefore you can grind the cumin here for the health
purpose directly without sort of doing it like by chewing it. וטורפין
לה יין ושמן, vetarfin lah yayin veshemen, and you can beat wine
and oil together
in a dish. Now the which it said as well that if
you didn't do it before שבת, Shabbat, you can put it on
separately but you don't beat it together. It never is clear what
exactly is the problem about beating it together. It might be that
the problem is like you're not supposed to do a lot of
types of
medical... Of course, that would be quite ironic because then it's not
a biblical concern and we don't basically apply the problem
about medicinal, not medical, medicinal treatments for חולה שאין בו סכנה. choleh
she'ein bo sakana. You don't even have to have a סכנה. sakana.
So why that should be an issue and it's very—people don't really
talk so much about what is the big problem about the wine
and oil. I did find the תפארת ישראל, Tiferes Yisrael, one of
a commentator on the משנה Mishna relatively recent, whatever, about I think
150 years ago, maybe 200 years ago. Anyway, he basically says that
maybe it's a concern because it looks too much like, you know,
what types of things you beat together friskily in a dish? It's
like when you're about to cook something, like you're about to fry
an egg, you beat an egg together, you know, or you beat
some batter, you're about to make a cake. So he thinks maybe
it's not just an issue of a—again, it's still rabbinic—but it's not
just an issue about medicinal because that we would waive immediately if
there was a חולה choleh case. So anyway, there's some concern about
beating this oil and wine together. We do it on שבת, Shabbos,
not, you know, separately; on יום טוב Yom Tov we can do
it directly. So אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, Amar lei Abaye l'Rav
Yosef, so Abaye said to Rav Yosef: מאי שנא כמון ביום טוב
דחזי לקדירה? Mai shna kamun b'Yom Tov d'chazi l'kdeira? So why do
we allow you to grind the cumin on יום טוב Yom Tov
for the child, for the infant, because in theory you could put
it in your pot, so it's a type of thing that could
be done on יום טוב? Yom Tov? So יין ושמן חזי נמי
בשבת לחולה? Yayin veshemen chazi nami b'Shabbos l'choleh? So similar—almost the same
point I made, but we'll see—which is that, you know, a normal
חולה choleh you're allowed to mix wine and oil together on שבת.
Shabbos. So why can't you do it for this infant in a
normal way? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the ברייתא: Beraita: אין טורפין
יין ושמן לחולה בשבת. Ein torfin yayin veshemen l'choleh b'Shabbos. You cannot
mix wine and oil together for a חולה choleh on שבת. Shabbos.
אמר רבן שמעון בן אלעזר משום רבי מאיר, Amar Rabban Shimon ben
Elazar mishum Rabbi Meir, Shimon Elazar says in the name of Rabbi
Meir: אף טורפין יין ושמן. Af torfin yayin veshemen. No, you can.
אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, now Shimon
Elazar said: פעם אחת חשש רבי מאיר בבני מעיו, Pa'am achat chashash
Rabbi Meir b'vnei me'av, one time Rabbi Meir had a stomach ache
on שבת, Shabbos, ובקשנו לטרוף לו יין ושמן, uvikashnu litroaf lo yayin
veshemen, and we wanted to beat for him wine and oil on
שבת Shabbos together, ולא הניחנו, v'lo hinichanu, and he didn't allow us
to do it. אמרנו לו, Amarnu lo, we said to him: דבריך
יבטלו בחייך? Devarecha yibatlu bechayecha? Your own words should be nullified in
your life? Right? We can't—you can't even פסקן, pasken, we can't even
follow your פסק psak for you yourself? So אמר לנו, amar lanu,
he said back to us: אף על פי שאני אומר כך, Af
al pi she'ani omer kach, even though I say what I do
that you can do this, וחברי אומרים כך, vechaverai omrim kach, and
my colleagues disagree with me and say you cannot do it, מימי
לא מלאני לבי לעבור על דברי חברי, Miyami lo milani libi la'avor
al divrei chaverai, in my entire life, I never went against the
opinion of my colleagues. If they outvote me, I'm not going to
go against them, even for myself. So the גמרא—so Gemara very impressive,
and therefore he didn't even take care of his stomach on שבת.
Shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara comments on this: הוא ניהו דמחמיר אנפשיה.
Hu nihu d'machmir anafshei. He was being strict on himself, אלא לכולי
עלמא—but ela l'kulei alma he wasn't really reversing his approach. His opinion
was still his opinion. He still believed that the הלכה halacha should
be that for everybody it should be שרי, shari, it should be
permissible. So therefore the גמרא Gemara assumes if that's Rabbi Meir and
a סתם משנה stam Mishna is Rabbi Meir, why does our משנה
Mishna have a problem doing it for the infant on שבת Shabbos
if you could do it for any חולה choleh on שבת? Shabbos?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: לא. התם לא בעי ליכא, הכא
בעי ליכא. Lo. Hatam lo ba'ei leicha, hacha ba'ei leicha. There by
the normal חולה, choleh, you don't have to beat it extremely well
together. Here it has to be very vigorous. So even that even
Rabbi Meir would not allow. So the גמרא Gemara says: הכא נמי
נעביד ולא ליכא. Hacha nami ne'avid v'lo leicha. Here too, so okay,
don't do it vigorously. Mix it without doing it vigorously. The גמרא
Gemara says: היינו דקתני נותן זה בפני עצמו וזה בפני עצמו. Hainu
d'katani noten zeh bifnei atzmo vezeh bifnei atzmo. So that's why we
say when it says you put them separately, it doesn't literally mean
separately, it means you don't beat them together vigorously. So whatever the
problem is with this wine and oil, if it's a general חולה
choleh problem, it seems like it's something in addition to a general
חולה choleh problem. A general חולה choleh problem, again, you're allowed to
do, but whatever the problem is, we might allow it for a
normal חולה, choleh, without beating it vigorously, but for some—but we don't
allow it for, again, for the infant, which is again quite surprising
because otherwise we would consider the infant חולה שיש בו סכנה, choleh
she'yesh bo sakana, but again the basic point here being, if there's
ways to do it that's not going to impact the treatment, then
you try to do it in the slightly different ways, which is
not the normal approach we have by somebody who's an obvious חולה
שיש בו סכנה. choleh she'yesh bo sakana. Yes, Rivka? So this phenomena
of the Rabbi prescribing one way for everybody and not for himself.
Right. We had that in Flatbush with the עירוב Eruv when they
first put up the Flatbush עירוב, Eruv, there were many Rabbis who
were for the עירוב, Eruv, but they wouldn't use it themselves. And
then in Riverdale. Really? Rabbi Willig does that? That creates an elitist
type of like, "it's okay for you guys but you're not on
my level." Right. I'm on such a high level I can't do
it. I find that very upsetting. No, I think you're right, and
I think that there's a, you know, I do think that there's
a value of an idea of each person, not only a Rabbi,
finding areas to be sort of מחמיר machmir on as a way
of giving expression to the idea that, you know, sometimes You know,
we don't, we try to be sort of like maximalists and we
try to excel and we try to do more and now more
could not necessarily only mean in a חומרא *chumra* way, we could
do more in terms of בין אדם לחברו *bein adam l'chavero*, more
in terms of, but I do think there's a value in giving
a certain expression to a certain idea of being a מחמיר *machmir*,
of giving expression to that great concern of like punctiliousness and דקדוק
*dikduk* and concern for violation that sometimes doesn't play itself out in
other areas. So finding, you know, to be מחמיר *machmir* in certain
areas, again, they should be well chosen and then, you know, in
terms of what are the broader implications for other people and for
your family and so on, that to me I think there's a
value in that. But I think though at a very personal private
level, okay, but I know, but I'm saying for somebody whose responsibility
it is to, you know, to sort of for the sake of
the ציבור *tzibbur* to attest to the acceptability of a certain type
of a thing and to, you know, and that they're relying on
him, I agree with you that I think that that creates a
very different type of a dynamic because what does it mean that
you're, you know, you're not doing it and I am doing it?
And you know, that sends a very different type of a message.
You want to have some חומרא *chumra* privately in your house about
something you're not giving a הכשר *hechsher* to, you know, I think
is very different, right? If I in my house want to keep
חדש *chadash*, but I say I don't, you know, or I personally,
I keep רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam*, I wait 72 minutes after שבת
Shabbos *Shabbos*, somebody asks me what's the הלכה halacha *halacha*? I might
say, look, I personally keep רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam*, but the הלכה
*halacha* is, is that you know, the פסק *psak* is, you know,
we normally go by like 45, 42 minutes, 45 minutes or whatever.
I don't think you have a problem with that. The problem isn't
when... Right, when the thing that they are supervising and telling people
to rely on them for they themselves are not doing. Now, it
I do want to say though one thing about this, which is
it's tricky because it's one thing, and then we have to move
on, it's one thing when, you know, it's an issue of like
כשרות *kashrus* where or something like, or let's say the עירוב *eruv*,
where the reason I'm not relying on it is because I don't
think it was done to a high enough standard. Wait a minute,
wait a minute, but by the עירוב *eruv* I understand. So by
כשרות *kashrus* you could really be concerned: if you're not going to
eat there then why should, how can you tell me to eat
there? You're basically saying that it's not done at a high enough
standard, well then it needs to be done at a higher standard.
But by the עירוב *eruv* there's some people that hold that no
matter how well the עירוב *eruv* is done they don't rely, they
don't use עירובים *eruvs* because they, you know, they, because all עירובים
*eruvs* rely on the assumption that our basic streets nowadays are not
רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim*. So that's a halachic question: can we, do
we פסק'ן *pasken* that way or not פסק'ן *pasken* that way? So
it has nothing to do with standard, it has to do with
a position of פסק
*psak*. You know, so let's say, I'll just give you a scenario
and then I'll move on, let's say I פסק'ן *pasken* that this,
that this bakery was okay, but not for people that keep חדש
*chadash*. If you keep חדש *chadash* it's not okay. I'm not saying
it's ישן *yashan*, but it's okay for everybody who doesn't keep חדש
*chadash*. It's okay for everybody who doesn't keep חלב ישראל *chalav Yisrael*.
I happen to keep חדש *chadash* and חלב ישראל *chalav Yisrael*, right?
So I don't think you necessarily feel the same way because there
it's a halachic issue, it's not a standard issue. And some people
follow certain הלכות *halachos* and some people, you know, some people follow
certain halachic positions and other people don't. So it's not so black
and white about those cases. Right, I mean, I think if somebody
gets up and says look, this עירוב *eruv* is 100% כשר *kosher*
for everybody who follows the position that we don't have רשות הרבים
*reshus harabbim* nowadays unless there's 600,000 people. There are people that don't
follow that position and wouldn't use an עירוב *eruv* anywhere no matter
how good it was. And obviously those people won't use this עירוב
*eruv*. You know, so, I mean, and again, I think but I
do think it's a good point. Anyway, here רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*,
something for a longer discussion, here רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* was not
telling other people to rely on him, he was just saying a
halachic position. Let's move on. תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabanan*: אין מסננין את
החרדל *ein masnenin es hachardal*, now that we're talking about things you
can do on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* or יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom
Tov*, okay, so you cannot filter a mustard במסננת שלו *b'misnenes shelo*,
this is on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*. ואין ממתקין אותו
בגחלת *v'ein mematkin oso begachal* so you don't sweeten it with a
coal. Apparently they would like press a coal against the mustard and
somehow that would be part of the process of making it and
that would cause the coal to go out. אמר ליה אביי לרב
יוסף Amrei lei Abaye l'Rav Yosef: *amar lei Abaye l'Rav Yosef*, or
partly go out, so אביי Abaye *Abaye* said to רב יוסף Rav
Yosef: *Rav Yosef*, מאי שנא מהא דתנן *mai shna meihai ditnan*, how
is it different than that which we taught in the משנה mishnah.
*mishna*? נותנין ביצה Beitzah, במסננת של חרדל *nosin beitza b'misnenes shechardal*, you
can pass an egg through a filter that you use for mustard
because the mustard filter still has this dark yellow color on it
because the mustard went through it, so when the egg goes through
it the egg gets more yellow. אמר ליה Amrei lei: *amar lei*:
התם לא מיחזי כבורר הכא מיחזי כבורר *hasam lo meichzi k'vorer hacha
meichzi k'vorer*. There it's not like בורר borer? *borer* because there the
whole egg goes through, it just picks up the color, you're not
separating. various parts of the egg. Here, however, it does get separated
because different parts of the mustard do get separated. Now why does
it just say it looks like בורר? borer, Why don't we say
it really is בורר? So if you look at תוספות, Tosfos, תוספות
Tosfos says הכא מחזי כבורר. hacha meichzi keborer. תוספות Tosfos says מיהו
בורר לא הוי, mihu borer lo havie, it's not real בורר, שגם
הפסולת ראוי לאכילה, shegam hapsolous roy l'achila, even what you're separating, right,
you could eat it, you could eat the stuff that was separated
out. It was edible without removing it. And you are allowed to
pour certain things, liquids in particular, through filters if the liquid could
have been drank without without having gone through. So it here but
anyway at least it is separating two parts as opposed to the
egg, it's just passing through to pick up the color. Okay, now
moving on. ואין ממתקינין אותו בגחלת, V'ein mematkinin oso b'kachles, you don't
sweeten it with the coal. והתניא ממתקינין אותו בגחלת? Veha-tanya mematkinin oso
b'kachles? We have a ברייתא Braisa that says you can. So לא
קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. כאן בגחלת של מתכת כאן בגחלת
של עץ. Kan b'kachal she'l mateses, kan b'kachal she'l eitz. It depends
whether it is a hot burning piece of metal or hot burning
piece of wood. Why is it different? Because the problem is כיבוי,
kibuy, extinguishing. And the real issue of extinguishing, the only way you
can really do the מלאכה melacha of extinguishing biblically is if you
do it to create something constructive, not just to stop the fire.
What do you do constructively? You make an ember, you make a
coal, or you only make a coal if you're dealing with wood.
You don't make a coal if you're dealing with metal. So therefore
when you're dealing with metal you're not even in the biblical category
at all, there's no way you could do biblical כיבוי kibuy with
metal. Okay, which raises interesting questions about turning about lights, and about
turning off gas in your oven when there is no coal that
remains. Okay, now nobody says it's מותר, muttar, but it takes it
out of the biblical category. And here you're doing it for the
sake of food on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay, so אמר ליה
אביי amrei lei Abaye so now אביי Abaye says to רב יוסף:
Rav Yosef "Okay, but even if it's biblical you're doing it for
food. מאי שנא מבישרא אגומרי? Mai shna mibishra agumrei? We allow you
to cook meat right on coals even though by placing it right
on the coals it causes the coals to you know somewhat extinguish.
That's okay, it's all food preparation on יום טוב. Yom Tov, So
why should it matter?" אמר ליה: Amrei lei: התם לא אפשר הכא
אפשר. Hasam lo efshar, hacha efshar. There there's no alternative. There the
so therefore you're allowed to on יום טוב. Yom Tov Here there's
an alternative, you can use metal. Which gets to a much larger
conversation which we're not going to have now, we'll have when we
get to ביצה, Beitzah, which is: you can do אוכל נפש ochel
nefesh on יום טוב, Yom Tov but what about if it was
ways to do it without you know violating without doing a מלאכה?
melacha? You could have gotten the same result without doing a מלאכה.
melacha. Are you allowed to do it or not? Or do you
have to try to minimize the מלאכה melacha that is being done?
It's a bigger issue when we come to מכשירי אוכל נפש, machshirei
ochel nefesh, things that could have been done from beforehand. If things
wanted you know you want to do on יום טוב Yom Tov?
itself, normally there's not a sense of limiting the way it's done,
but if it really needed to have been done on יום טוב
Yom Tov itself. But nevertheless this is what's being discussed and he
says maybe if there's an alternative even if it's about preparation of
food you should not be doing it. אמר ליה Amrei lei: אביי
Abaye לרב יוסף: מהו לגבן? Mahu legabein? Can you make cheese on
יום טוב? Yom Tov, אמר amar, ליה: אסור, Assur, you can't. מאי
שנא מלישה? Mai shna milisha? How's it different than kneading bread? You
know you're taking things you're bringing component parts together, you're giving it
a form. Why is one allowed and one not allowed? It's all
יום טוב Yom Tov, it's all food. אמר ליה: התם לא אפשר
הכא אפשר. Hasam lo efshar, hacha efshar. Same point. There it's not
possible—not impossible, but who wants stale bread? So there's a reason to
do it דווקא davka on יום טוב, Yom Tov. so therefore you're
allowed. Here if it could have been done before יום טוב, Yom
Tov. you should do it before יום טוב. Yom Tov. So now
that's a different point. That's not like it had to be done
today but it could be done in a way with lesser violation:
metal rather than wood. Here it's the point is that it it
you know it could have been done yesterday. So it could have
been done yesterday that might really change the equation. So the גמרא
Gemara says: One minute. ואמרי נהרדאי גבינה בר יומא מעליא. V'amri Nahardai:
gvina bar yoma me'alya. Don't they say in נהרדעי Nahardai that cheese
of today is good? I mean not day-old, cheese of today is
good, that actually fresh cheese is good. So therefore you should you
could have done it on יום טוב. Yom Tov, הכי קאמר, hachi
ka'amar, this is what they mean: אפילו גבינה בר יומא מעליא, afilu
gvina bar yoma me'alya, even if it's fresh it's good, but cheese
is better or at least as good if it's the day done
a day before. So here we get very interesting ideas which we'll
have to revisit when we get to ביצה, Beitzah. which is: you're
allowed to do food preparation on יום טוב. Yom Tov. What if
you can do it in a way that is less fewer מלאכות?
melachos? Are you do you have to try to choose the approach
that is fewer מלאכות? melachos? Or is there basically a complete you
know waiving of all מלאכות melachos in the context of food preparation?
Then the other question is: not fewer מלאכות melachos but you could
have done it just as well yesterday. And how much therefore are
you do you have to do it yesterday and not today? So
two very important possible qualifications which we'll see more when we get
to ביצה. Back to ברית מילה. bris milah. Yes. Is there a
נולד nolad issue though about making cheese on Shabbat? Yeah but this
is יום טוב, יום טוב. I mean you can make I'm not
exactly what are the parameters of נולד nolad but like you can
make bread, you know, which is also just as much like the
גמרא Gemara says, you take flour and next thing you have a
cake, you know, it's a so alright. אין עושים לכלוך Ein osim
luchluch but you do not make a little like garment a wrap
around around it which is to protect the you know the thing
from the מילה milah from reversing itself. So it says you don't
make but you I mean you can wrap a piece of garment
but not like this very like you know specific. Specifically made bandage,
which you know again is more than is needed to be done
on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*. אמר אביי Amar Abaye, *amar Abaye* said אביי
Abaye *Abaye*, אמרה לי אם amra li em, *amrah li em* my
quote-unquote mother, my nursemaid said to me, האי חלוקא דינוקא *hai chaluka
deyanuka* this bandage, you know literally like garment that they make for
the infant for the ברית מילה bris milah. *bris milah*, לפניה לסטרא
דעילאי *lifneih listara de'ilai* you should turn the stitching to the outside,
דילמא מדבק גרדא מיניה *dilma midbak garda minei* maybe a strand from
the stitching will stick to like you know a piece of skin
from the, you know near the incision, ואתי לידי כרישתבכנא *ve'ati lidei
krishtavkhan* then when you remove it, it'll you know it could seriously
injure the infant and you know injure his genitals. So אימיה דאביי
*eimeih de'Abaye*, so Abaye's mother again nursemaid, עבדה כיסה לפלגא דפלגא *avda
kisa lepalga depalga*. So when she would apparently she was sort of
like a you know somebody that because he's always quoting her in
terms of these sort of medical issues and medicinal issues, she was
people that you know treated or helped a lot of people. So
when she would be helping people for these making these things for
their infants for ברית מילה bris milah, *bris milah*, she made it
that there was a cover like a sheath that went into this
into this like cloth into this like you know bandage halfway down
so that basically it would protect the wound from the edge and
therefore so when you pulled it off, you know it would be
like it would be like an inner lining so it wouldn't rub
up against the stitching it would not create this problem. אמר אביי
Abaye *amar Abaye*, Abaye said האי ינוקא דלית ליה חלוקא *hai yanuka
delait lei chaluka* if the infant does not have this type of
a special garment, you know for the point of incision, ליתי בליסא
*leiti blisa* you should take a worn-out cloth, דאית ליה סיפסא *de'it
lei sipsa* that has an actual an edge to it, a what's
it called, a hem, thank you, וליחייה לסיפסא לתתאי *velichayei lesipsa letatai*
and that should be at the bottom because obviously it should be
away from the point of incision, but that helps sort of keep
it in its place, ואיפיה לעילאי *ve'aifeih le'ilai* and you should extend
this thing above to cover the point of incision, the cloth. ואמר
אביי v'amar Abaye, *ve'amar Abaye*, Abaye says, אמרה לי אם amra li
em *amrah li em* my mother said to me, האי ינוקא דלא
ידעה מפשעתיה *hai yanuka delo yada mifsatei* one minute, let me just
check רש״י Rashi *Rashi* here, right, so an infant that you don't
know that you cannot see where his anus is. I don't know
exactly how that would happen but anyway, לשפייה משחא *leshafeih mishkha* so
what you should do is you should rub him with oil, ולווקמיה
להדי יומא *velukmeih lahadei yoma* and put him opposite the sun, והיכא
דזיג *ve'heika de'zig* and where you see it's sort of like it's
more translucent, וליקרעיה בשערתא *ulikreih bisha'arta* you should tear with a the
point of a barley seed. Apparently the point of a barley seed
was pointy but it would not be dangerous and that would be
the place in which in you know where the anus was apparently
I don't know does that ever happen? Like an imperforate anus. An
imperforate anus. Okay. So there you go. So very interesting. Wow. Okay.
So here's what he says. You identify where the location is by
seeing where it's somewhat a little bit more translucent and then you
should tear it. Okay, שתי וערב *shesi ve'erev* like you know sort
of horizontal and vertical. אבל בכלי מתכות לא *aval bichli matakhtos lo*
but you should not use a metal instrument to cut, משום mishum
דזריז *mishum de'zariz* because that will actually like you know injure. ואמר
אביי Abaye *ve'amar Abaye* and Abaye said, אמרה לי אם *amrah li
em* my mother said to me, האי ינוקא דלא מייץ *hai yanuka
delo mayit* if you have an infant that does not is not
sucking, you know nursing from his mother, מיגר דקר פומיה *migar dekar
pumeih* his lips are like like heavy, not heavy excuse me cold.
So מאי תקנתיה *mai takanteih* what do you do? ליתי כסא דגומרי
*leiti kasa degumrei* you should take a vessel filled with like embers,
sort of like the משה רבינו *Moshe Rabbeinu* story, right? No, but
ולנקטיה ליה להדי פומיה *velinketeih lei lahadei pumeih* and should put it
near his mouth. דחים פומיה *dechayim pumeih* it'll warm up his mouth
and מייץ *mayit* and he will suck. Does that happen that infants
are some infants won't take to their mother? And what's normally the
cause of that? A lot of times it's sometimes they have a
kind of a slow transition to extrauterine life and they're not really
able to latch and sometimes they have neurological problems. Interesting. Huh. Okay.
Alright. So anyway, so this believed that it was having to do
with cold. ואמר אביי *ve'amar Abaye*, Abaye said, אמרה לי אם *amrah
li em* my mother said, האי ינוקא *hai yanuka* you see that
she really worked with these infants, האי ינוקא דלא מנשנתי *hai yanuka
delo minshantei* that does not really like רש״י *Rashi* says is like
you know breathe out, so לנפפיה בנפששתא *linfapeih binafshasta* you should like
fan him with a like a like he says like a sieve.
Actually רש״י *Rashi* says that you can't hear a heartbeat. Excuse me,
you don't really hear his heartbeat, so you should fan him with
a sieve. Okay. ואמר אביי *ve'amar Abaye* says, אמרה לי אם *amrah
li em*, האי ינוקא דלא מעווי *hai yanuka delo ma'avi* if you
have an infant that is not that is not really like breathing
well. דלא מפי, ליתו שליתא leiseiy shalisah דאימיה, d'imei, you should take
the mother's placenta from the mother, obviously we're talking that he was
just born, ולישפיה v'lishpey and you should rub it on him, ומפי
u-mafi and then he'll be able to breathe better. ואמר אביי, and
אביי said, אמרה לי אם, my mother said, האי ינוקא דקטין, hai
yanuka d'katin, if you have an infant that is too like you
know thin, too frail, ליתו שליתא leiseiy shalisah דאימיה, d'imei, again you
should take the placenta, וליסרקיה עלויה v'lisrakey iluvei and you should rub
it on him, מקטנא לאומא, mi-kutna l'uma, from the narrow part to
the wide part. So the sort of you know symbolic that the
narrow should become wide, he should put on weight if he's not
if you know if he has a very low birth weight. ואלים
v'alim and if he has too weighty, רש"י Rashi points out we
don't mean because of health that he's heavy, but we mean like
he has like some type of an inflammation or you know he's
like you know puffed up because obviously you know now you know
now it's you know thin is identified with healthy but then the
heavier you were the healthier you were. So רש"י Rashi wants it's
what? Still for babies the higher birth weight is still... Right, that's
true, but but I assume that you could have a very large
baby nowadays which we wouldn't say necessarily is healthy, right? I mean
there's still like a norm, isn't there? We don't say that bigger
is always better, right? So anyway okay. So רש"י Rashi makes the
point though that there's actually anyway. So he's too heavy whatever the
reason is. So what do you do? ואלים... v'alim... so מאומא לקטנא,
mei-uma l'kutna, so you rub the placenta on him from the wide
part to the narrow part. Okay. ואמר ליה אביי v'amar leh Abaye
and אביי says, אמרה לי אם my mother said to me... where
were we... האי ינוקא דסומק hai yanuka d'sumak and now here's very
very relevant, if you have an infant that is too ruddy, דאכתי
לא איבלע ביה דמא d'akati lo ivlah bei dama and therefore the
blood is not completely absorbed yet into his skin into his body,
that's one thing they understood it to mean. לתרחו ליה litrichu leh
you have to wait עד דאיבלע ביה דמא ad d'ivlah bei dama
until until the blood gets absorbed ולמהליה v'limhaleiah and then to give
him a ברית מילה. bris milah. He's not yet ready for ברית
מילה, bris milah it'd be too risky. דירוק d'yarok if he's jaundice
דאכתי לא נפל ביה דמא d'akati lo nafal bei dama which is
interpreted to mean that the blood is not yet well enough flowing
in him. It's also dangerous. לתרחו ליה עד דנפל ביה דמא litrichu
leh ad d'nafal bei damei wait until the blood falls into him
like starts flowing well, ולמהליה v'limhaleiah and then give him a ברית
מילה. bris milah דתניא d'tanya it was taught in a ברייתא, braitah,
אמר רבי נתן, amar Rabbi Natan, רבי נתן Rabbi Natan said, פעם
אחת הלכתי לכרכי הים paam achat halachti l'karchei hayam once I went
to some overseas island, ובאה אשה לפני u-ba'ah ishah l'fanai a woman
came to me, שמלה בנה ראשון ומת ושני ומת, she-malah b'nah rishon
vamet v'sheni vamet, her first son after the ברית מילה bris milah,
died, the second one after the ברית מילה bris milah, died. שלישי,
shlishi, thirdly, sometimes this is an example about a case of a
hemophiliac but here apparently that's not the story. שלישי הביאתו לפני shlishi
hevi'atu l'fanai the third one she brought him to me, וראיתיו שהוא
אדום, v'reitiv she-hu adom, I saw he was very red. אמרתי לה,
amarti lah, I said to her, המתיני לו עד שיבלע בו דמו
himtini lo ad she-yibal'ah bo damo wait until the blood gets absorbed
into him. המתינה himtinah she waited לו עד שיבלע בו דמו lo
ad she-yibal'ah bo damo until the blood got absorbed, ומלה אותו u-malah
oto and she gave him a ברית מילה, bris milah. וחי v'chai
and he lived. והיו קורין אותו נתן הבבלי על שמי v'hayu korin
oto Natan ha-Bavli al shemi and they called him נתן הבבלי Natan
ha-Bavli after me. Okay. שוב פעם אחת shuv paam achat once... what?
Yes. שוב פעם אחת shuv paam achat once
הלכתי למדינת קפוטקיא halachti l'medinat Kaputkia I went to the country of
קפוטקיא, Kapotkia, where is that? Cappadocia.
Yeah, we had that before. Cappadocia.
Greece or something?
It's in southern Turkey today. It wasn't Turkey then. Okay.
ובאה אשה אחת לפני u-ba'ah ishah achat l'fanai
a woman came to me, שמלה בנה ראשון ומת ושני ומת. she-malah
b'nah rishon vamet v'sheni vamet. שלישי הביאתו לפני shlishi hevi'atu l'fanai the
third one she first two died, third one she brought him. וראיתיו
v'reitiv I saw שהוא ירוק she-hu yarok that he was jaundice. הצצתי
בו hitzatzti bo I looked closely at him, ולא ראיתי בו דם
ברית v'lo reiti bo dam brit I did not see apparently in
the you know at the genitals that there was blood that would
be at the place of the incision. So presumably there would again
be this health concern there, you know you don't want the blood
to be too much to the surface but you don't want there
to be not present at all. So it was sort of the
opposite concern. אמרתי לה המתיני לו עד שיפול בו דמו amarti lah
himtini lo ad she-yipol bo damo wait until the blood sort of
is going through the body better. והמתינה לו v'himtinah lo she waited,
ומלה אותו u-malah oto and she gave him a ברית מילה, bris
milah, וחי v'chai and he lived. והיו קורין שמו נתן הבבלי על
שמי v'hayu korin shemo Natan ha-Bavli al shemi and they called him
נתן הבבלי Natan ha-Bavli after me. Now according to this it's all
a medical decision. By the way, it does raise issues why אביי
had to quote his nursemaid because that's in the Amoratic period and
here you have a ברייתא braitah that says exactly that point, so
that's quite interesting. But also here it's all done from a medical
perspective. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi here makes an
important addition which leads to a whole other issue around ברית מילה.
Bris Milah רש"י Rashi says לכרכי הים, l'karchei hayam, two lines from
the bottom, הכי גרסינן, hachi garsinan, וראיתיו שהוא ירוק, v'reitiv she-hu yarok,
הצצתי בו ולא היה בו דם ברית, hitzatzti bo v'lo hayah bo
dam brit, תרתי לטיבותא, tartei l'tivuta, there are two problems. חדא דאי
מהיל ליה chada d'ei mahil leh if you give him a ברית
מילה, Bris Milah לא נפיק מיניה דמא lo nafik mineih dama blood
won't come out. והטפת דם ברית מצוה v'hatafat dam brit mitzvah and
it's a mitzvah for... to come out when you do the incision.
Now הטפת דם ברית hatafas dam bris is mentioned when you can't
give a ברית מילה Bris Milah, when the child is already circumcised
or didn't have a foreskin, but רש"י Rashi is saying even when
you do the ברית מילה Bris Milah there's a מצוה mitzvah that
the blood should come out כדכתיב גם את בדם בריתך k'dichtiv gam
at b'dam britecha even with you with the blood of your covenant.
Okay, are here mentioned the other פסוק pasuk that we quote at
the ברית מילה, Bris Milah בדמי חיי. b'damayich chayi. And number two
there's a problem that it's an it's that there's a health issue
and a danger issue. So what winds up happening is particularly in
the post-Talmudic period is the role of blood in the ברית מילה
Bris Milah becomes much more so the forefront on and a much
more central part to the point you know that there's questions about
can you use a clamp that cuts off the blood before you
cut so when you cut there won't be any blood that comes
off and you know it goes back to the ברית מילה Bris
Milah story with צפורה, Tzippora, right? It says because it says you
know what's the פסוק pasuk חתן דמים למולות. chatan damim lamulot. So
the role of blood in the ברית מילה Bris Milah, there's interesting
literature around that, but you don't really see it in the גמרא,
Gemara, you really see it much more after the you see it
a little bit before the גמרא Gemara in some like I said
in the צפורה Tzippora story and others, but but anyway in the
גמרא's Gemara definition of ברית מילה Bris Milah, blood's not focused so
much as it does after the גמרא. Gemara.
So you think there needs to be blood and a-?
I'm not giving פסק הלכה psak halacha here. Let's look at the
next משנה. mishnah, Okay, you're playing the role of Michael in
his absence.
Okay, קלד עמוד ב, kuf lamed daled amud beis, מרחיצין את הקטן
בין לפני מילה בין לאחר המילה. marchitzin es hakatan bein lifnei milah
bein l'achar hamilah. You now bathe the infant whether before or after
the ברית מילה, Bris Milah. presumably even if you have to heat
up water, this is again a health issue. ומזלפין עליו ביד אבל
לא בכלי umizalfin alav biyadh aval lo bichli and you can sprinkle
water on him with your hand but not directly with a vessel
which is interesting. What about the fact that before it sounded like
just go ahead and do it? So we'll see in the גמרא.
Gemara. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר מרחיצין את הקטן ביום השלישי, Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaryah omer marchitzin es hakatan bayom hashlishi, you not only
do it on the day, you can even do it on the
third day שחל להיות בשבת shechal lihyot b'Shabbos even if the third
day falls on שבת Shabbos שנאמר ויהי ביום השלישי בהיותם כואבים, shenemar
vayihi bayom hashlishi biheyotam koavim, on the third day when they were
in dire pain, that's when שמעון ולוי Shimon v'Levi came in and
wiped out the town of שכם. Shechem. So you see the third
day is a particular day of vulnerability and therefore even the third
day you can do this. Now ספק safek if a child is
a doubtful, now it could mean doubtful whether he was born on
שבת Shabbos. or or on the weekday, but רש"י Rashi says here
we'll see what the גמרא Gemara says that it means that he
was doubtful in the sense that he might not have been a
full nine months old baby, he might have been born in the
eighth month. And that leads to the fact you know that חז"ל
Chazal felt an eight month old baby won't live and therefore you
can't violate שבת Shabbos. for him. So we'll look about what ספק
safek is. ואנדרוגינוס, ve-androgynos, an androgynous who has both male and female
genitalia, אין מחללין עליו את השבת, ein mechalelin alav es ha-Shabbos, you
don't override שבת Shabbos, for the ספק safek for obvious reasons and
for the אנדרוגינוס androgynos that even though he has male genitalia in
the eighth day maybe he's not fully defined הלכתית halachically as male.
רבי יהודה מתיר באנדרוגינוס, Rabbi Yehuda matir be-androgynos, but רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says no, for an אנדרוגינוס androgynos you can, he has male
genitalia, eighth day, it's a definite ברית מילה, bris milah, you do
it even on שבת. Shabbos, So that'll be very interesting the end
of that משנה, mishnah that'll be tomorrow. Today we focus on the
first part which which really you know ends the discussion about health
issues on שבת. Shabbos. So first we the issue about heating up
water and bathing him. So the גמרא Gemara says אמרת רישא מרחיצין,
amarta reisha marchitzin, first you said you can bathe, which means with
no limitations, and then you said you can only sprinkle the water
with the
hand. You so רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, רבה בר אבוה Rabbah bar
Avuha דאמרי תרווייהו, d'amri tarvaihu, both said כיצד תני, keitzad tani, the
משנה mishnah first means how do you מרחיץ? marchitz? You can be
מרחיץ, marchitz, you can bathe. How? By hand, not with a vessel.
מרחיצין
את הקטן בין לפני מילה בין לאחר מילה. marchitzin es hakatan bein
lifnei milah bein l'achar hamilah. Here's how you read it: you can
bathe the infant. כיצד, keitzad, now
under in what exactly how do you go about that? מזלפין עליו
ביד אבל לא בכלי, mizalfin alav biyadh aval lo bichli, use a
hand but not a vessel. Okay, so that's a severe limitation on
the משנה mishnah that it can only it cannot be done in
the normal way, similar to the things about chewing the cumin and
whatever. אמר רבא והא מרחיצין תני, amar Rava v'ha marchitzin tani, said
רבא, Rava, you can't say that, it says מרחיצין, marchitzin, which means
the normal way. אלא אמר רבא הכי תני, ela amar Rava hachi
tani, so rather רבא Rava said this is how to read: מרחיצין
את הקטן בין לפני המילה בין לאחר המילה. marchitzin es hakatan bein
lifnei hamilah bein l'achar hamilah. Period. You can bathe the infant the
normal way by heating up water on שבת, Shabbos. whether before or
after the ברית מילה. bris milah ביום הראשון כדרכו. bayom harishon k'darko.
Now that's on day one you can do it the normal way
even by straight heating up in the vessel, the whole thing. וביום
השלישי שחל להיות בשבת, uvayom hashlishi shechal lihyot b'Shabbos, however if it's
day three on שבת, Shabbos. then מזלפין עליו ביד אבל לא בכלי.
mizalfin alav biyadh aval lo bichli. I'm sorry, I don't give you
any same type of a license on day three. I know רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer gives you a license on day three, but I
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is the way he's reading the משנה
Mishna. says that if it's not day one it can only be
with the by hand and not by a vessel. You have to
do a שינוי. shinuy. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben
Azaryah omer, now רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah says
מרחיצין את הקטן ביום השלישי שחל להיות בשבת, marchitzin es hakatan bayom
hashlishi shechal lihyot b'Shabbos, even on day three you can bathe the
normal way שנאמר ויהי ביום השלישי בהיותם כואבים. shenemar vayihi bayom hashlishi
biheyotam koavim. So what רבא Rava basically says is the idea of
doing it in the not normal way is not for day one,
it's for day three, and that's the debate of the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma and רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, whether by day three you
can do it normal or not. Now what day have we not
mentioned here? Day two. Okay, so what's that? So רש״י basically assumes
that day two is like day one, that the whole issue, that
it's also an equal amount of danger, the whole issue is do
you say that it's still even as by day three? You didn't
have to read it that way. You could have said day one
is the danger, you know, and maybe, you know, maybe רב אלעזר
בן עזריה Rav Elazar ben Azaryah would say day two and day
three. Maybe he'd only say day three. Anyway, the question day two
is not being directly addressed. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. תניא כוותיה דרבא. Tanya kevasei de'Rava.
We taught like רבא. Rava. מרחיצין קטן בין לפני מילה ובין לאחר
מילה ביום הראשון כדרכו. Marchitzin katan bein lifnei milah u'vein le'achar milah
be'yom ha'rishon k'darko. You can bathe the infant before and after on
the first day the normal way. וביום השלישי שחל להיות בשבת, U'veyom
ha'shlishi she'chal lihyot be'Shabbos, if it's day three, then it can't be
the normal way, מזלפין עליו ביד. mezalfin alav be'yad. You have to
just do it with the hand. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר, Rebbi
Elazar ben Azaryah omer, רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah
says, מרחיצין את הקטן ביום השלישי שחל להיות בשבת, marchitzin et hakatan
beyom hashlishi she'chal lihyot be'Shabbos, even on day three you can do
it the normal way, ואף על פי שאין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר,
v'af al pi she'ein raya la'davar zecher la'davar, there's no absolute proof,
there's a hint to it, שנאמר ויהי ביום השלישי בהיותם כואבים. she'ne'emar
vay'hi bayom hashlishi biheyotam ko'avim. פסיק. Pasik. Okay, then then the ברייתא
Baraisa ends by saying וכשמזלפין, u'che'she'mezalfin, when they do sprinkle by hand,
אין מזלפין לא בכוס ולא בקערה ולא בכלי. ein mezalfin lo be'chos
v'lo be'ke'ara v'lo bi'chli. You don't like take a vessel or you
know like a cup or a dish or some type of vessel
and sprinkle, because you could sprinkle like that, you know, you don't
put him into like a little tub, but you could take a
vessel and use that to sprinkle. No, you don't. אלא ביד, ela
be'yad, you do it, you do it, you sprinkle with the hand.
That's when you do the sprinkling on day three. So the גמרא
Gemara just says אמר תנא קמא, amar Tanna Kamma, that's the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma who says day three you can only sprinkle. רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה's Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah position is on day three
you can do it normally. Okay, so that's the debate. Now the
and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma on day one allows it the
normal way. Now the גמרא Gemara just comments on רבי אלעזר בן
עזריה, Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah, מאי אף על פי שאין ראיה לדבר
זכר לדבר? mai af al pi she'ein raya la'davar zecher la'davar? What
do you mean there's even though there's no real proof there's a
hint to this idea that day three is different? משום
meaning what do you mean? Because I mean it seems like a
great proof. It says that day three they were vulnerable. So isn't
that a great proof? So the גמרא Gemara says no, משום דגדול
לא סליק בישרא היי, mishum d'gadol lo salik bisra hai, because an
adult the wound does not heal quickly. So for an adult even
by day three he could be in a status of סכנה. sakana.
קטן, Katan, but an infant, סליק בישרא היי, salik bisra hai, the
flesh you know sort of rises up meaning the wound heals very
quickly and therefore by day three already it's no longer a danger.
Okay, so you can't really prove it from the פסוק. pasuk. Now
a story. ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבא, Hahu d'ata l'kamei d'Rava, somebody came
to רבא. Rava. אורי ליה כשמעתיה, Uri leih k'shimateih, he ruled according
to his position. He basically ruled it's day one, you can heat
up water directly and do everything directly normally, put him into a
tub. איחלש, Ichlash, then the infant got sick.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, excuse
me, the question is איחלש רבא. ichlash Rava.
Yeah, I think it's
איחלש רבא, ichlash Rava, right, because רבא אמר. Rava amar. And then
איחלש רבא, ichlash Rava, so then רבא Rava got sick. Okay, so
אמר, he said, אנא בהדי תרגינא דסבי למה לי? ana bahadi targinna
de'savei lama li? Why did I have to get mixed up with
the way the elders interpreted it? Meaning because רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
and רבה בר אבוה Rabbah bar Avuha who were older than him
interpreted the ברייתא Baraisa in a more narrow way, in the משנה.
Mishna They said you can't do it the normal way on the
first day, you could only sprinkle. So רבא Rava here ruled that
you can do it the normal way, he got sick and he
thought maybe that was a sign that he overstepped his authority. He
should not have ruled he should not have ruled against the other
position that you could only sprinkle it. So אמרו ליה רבנן, amru
leih rabbanan, so the rabbis meaning the rabbinic students said to him,
לרבא, le'Rava, והתניא כוותיה דמר, ve'hatanya kevaseih de'mar, what do you mean?
We have a ברייתא Baraisa that supports your position. Why are you
now just because you got sick, why are you now having second
doubts, second thoughts? So אמר להו, amar lehu, he said back to
them, מתניתין כוותייהו דייקי. matnisin kevaseihu dayki. It's true the ברייתא Baraisa
supports my position, but the you know the close textual read of
the משנה Mishnah more implies their position. How is that? ממאי? Mimai?
Where do you get this from?
מדקתני רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר מרחיצין את הקטן ביום השלישי שחל
להיות בשבת, mide'ka'tani Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah omer marchitzin et hakatan beyom
hashlishi she'chal lihyot be'Shabbos, that he said you can bathe the infant
on day three that's on שבת. Shabbos. אי אמרת בשלמא תנא קמא
מזלפין קאמר, ei amrat bishlama Tanna Kamma mezalfin ka'amar, if the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma never meant any scenario, not even day one, that
you could bathe normally, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma only ever allowed
you to do זילוף zeeluf sprinkling, היינו דקתני רבי אלעזר בן עזריה,
hainu d'ka'tani Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah, so רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbi
Elazar ben Azaryah says I'm sorry, it's not just זילוף, zeeluf, מרחיצין,
marchitzin, you can actually do normal bathing and you could even do
it on day three. אלא אי אמרת תנא קמא מרחיצין ביום הראשון
קאמר, ela ei amrat Tanna Kamma marchitzin beyom harishon ka'amar, if the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma started by talking about normal bathing on day
one, ובמזלפין ביום השלישי, u'v'mezalfin beyom hashlishi, and on day three you
do the sprinkling, היי רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר מרחיצין, hai Rebbi
Elazar ben Azaryah omer marchitzin, when רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar
ben Azaryah says you can bathe, he shouldn't have just say you
can bathe on day three, he should have said אף מרחיצין מיבעי
ליה, af marchitzin mibayei leih, you can even bathe, meaning once the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma introduced the possibility if the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma had never introduced the possibility of normal bathing, then when רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah comes to state his position
he says you say sprinkle, I say bathe. But if the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma had said bathe on day one, sprinkle on day
three, then רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbi Elazar ben Azaryah should have
said on day three I also think he can bathe, just like
you thought he could bathe on day one. You know day three
is no different than day one. So because it didn't have that
word אף, af, it suggests to רבא Rava that the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma had never said you could do normal bathing and he's
having doubts. about his read that you could do normal bathing on
day one. Okay. דאתא רב דימי אמר רבי אלעזר, De-ata Rav Dimi
amar Rabi Elazar, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, he said in the name of רבי אלעזר, Rabi Elazar,
הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Halacha k'Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah. We rule
like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azariah, so the whole
debate what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds would be relatively moot
because we would hold like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben
Azariah, you could do normal bathing and you could even do it
on day three, not only on day one. Okay. הבעו בה במערבא.
Havu ba b'Ma'arava. Now they asked in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, when
we say you're allowed to bathe, הרחצת כל גופו, harchatzat kol gufo,
whether it's according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma or רבי אלעזר,
Rabbi Elazar, day one, day three, whenever you're allowed to bathe, הרחצת
כל גופו, harchatzat kol gufo, do we mean bathing the entire body,
or הרחצת מילה, harchatzat milah, or do we mean bathing the genitals
and the area of the incision, or at least genitals but not
the whole body? אמר להו ההוא מרבנן, Amar lehu hahu me-rabbanan, one
of the rabbis said to those that were asking the questions, this
anonymous group that was asking this question, רבי יעקב שמיה, Rabbi Yaakov
shemei, and רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov was the name of this rabbi,
מסתברא הרחצת כל גופו, mistavra harchatzat kol gufo, it makes sense to
say that what we're allowing is to bathe the whole body. ואי
סלקא דעתך הרחצת מילה, V'ee salka daitach harchatzat milah, if we're just
bathing the area of the ברית מילה, bris milah. so מי גרע
מחמין על גבי מכה, mi gara mechamin al gabei maka, you don't
need to tell me that this is a special הלכה by ברית
מילה bris milah and he's a סכנה. sakana. We always hold that
you're allowed to put hot water on a wound, you know, in
a normal case, even a normal wound. How do you know that?
דאמר רב, D'amar Rav, because רב Rav says, אין מונעין חמין ושמן
מעל גבי מכה בשבת. ein monin chamin v'shemen me-al gabei maka b'Shabbos.
You don't hold back hot water and oil from a wound on
שבת. Shabbos. Now תוספות Tosafot says it means a mixture of hot
water and oil which would be something that would be perceived like
a medicinal treatment. But obviously you could put hot water and oil
on other parts of the body, just סתם, stam, not necessarily on
a wound. Now of course the question is, when did the water
get heated up? So he understood that it might even mean the
water got heated up on שבת. Shabbos, So even if it were
a normal wound, which would be like wild, why would you be
able to do that if it was a normal wound? So that's
what the גמרא Gemara pushes back. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. מתקיף
לה רב יוסף, Matkif lah Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef,
asked on this. ולא שני לך בין חמין שהוחמו בשבת לחמין שהוחמו
מערב שבת? V'lo shani lach bein chamin she-huchmu b'Shabbos l'chamin she-huchmu m'erev
Shabbos? He says wait a minute. That's totally irrelevant. Yes, you can
put hot water on a wound if it was heated before שבת.
Shabbos? Then the only concern is like, no, סתם, stam, the rabbinic
problem of medicinal treatments on שבת. Shabbos. So fine, if it was
heated before שבת, Shabbos and it's hot water and oil, it's not
a big deal, whatever fine, you can do that. Okay, but but
here we're saying you can heat the water for the infant. So
we might be talking just for the area of the ברית מילה.
bris milah. You can't say it was obvious. What was obvious was
preheated water. But if you can actually heat the water, that's not
obvious. And maybe it's only for the area of the ברית מילה
bris milah. and not for the entire body. Okay, so that's a
very good response. So מתקיף לה רב דימי, Matkif lah Rav Dimi,
so רב דימי Rav Dimi said back to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef
why is that such a good point? He said וממאי דהכא בחמין
שהוחמו בשבת פליגי? U-mimai d'hacha b'chamin she-huchmu b'Shabbos paligi? What makes you
think here that when we say you can bathe the infant, we
mean you can heat up water on שבת? Shabbos? דילמא בחמין שהוחמו
מערב שבת פליגי. Dilma b'chamin she-huchmu m'erev Shabbos paligi. Maybe they debate,
meaning the rabbis and רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, about water that was
heated before שבת. Shabbos Why are you taking for granted that you
can heat up water on שבת Shabbos, for this infant? So אמר
אביי, אביי says, אנא הוה ידענא לשנויי ליה, ana hava yadana l'shanuyei
leh, I wanted to give the answer, וקדים ושני ליה רב יוסף,
v'kadim v'shani leh Rav Yosef, but רב יוסף Rav Yosef, beat me
and he gave the answer back before I could give the answer,
which is pretty funny because אביי was a student of רב יוסף,
Rav Yosef so he wanted to jump in and defend רב יוסף
Rav Yosef and then he got upset that רב יוסף defended himself.
But anyway, okay, so what here was the response to that, why
is it obvious to me that we're talking about heating up water
on שבת? Shabbos, מפני שסכנה היא לו, Mipnei she-sakana hi lo,
because the whole point of this משנה Mishnah, is that the infant
is considered to be in a סכנה. sakana. I mean and you
quote the פסוק, pasuk, ביום השלישי בהיותם כאבים, bayom hashlishi bi-hyotam ko'avim,
the whole point is that we're treating this not as a normal
type of just sick, but as a real סכנה. sakana. So therefore
the point is the משנה, Mishnah yes, normally you can put hot
water and oil on a wound on שבת Shabbos if it was
heated up before. That's just an issue about the rabbinic issue of
medicinal treatment. Our משנה is saying that you can heat it, we're
understanding it to say you can heat up water, and therefore we
can raise the question, heat up for the whole infant, or just
heat up for the area of the ברית מילה. איתמר נמי, Itmar
nami, it was taught similarly, כי אתא רבין אמר רבי אבהו אמר
רבי אלעזר, Ki ata Ravin amar Rabi Abbahu amar Rabi Elazar, ואמרי
לה אמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי יוחנן, v'amri lah amar Rabi Abbahu
amar Rabi Yochanan, in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan from
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, הלכה כרבי אלעזר בן עזריה, halacha k'Rabbi Elazar
ben Azariah, we rule like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben
Azariah, so even on day three, and even רחיצה, rechitza, not just
sprinkling, and not only that, בין בחמין שהוחמו בשבת בין בחמין שהוחמו
מערב שבת, bein b'chamin she-huchmu b'Shabbos bein b'chamin she-huchmu m'erev Shabbos,
whether with hot water that was heated on שבת, Shabbos. whether on
ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, so you can even heat up the water
on שבת, בין הרחצת כל גופו בין הרחצת מילה. bein harchatzat kol
gufo bein harchatzat milah. And now we hadn't resolved that before, but
now we're saying it can even be for the whole body, not
just for the area of the ברית מילה. מפני שסכנה היא לו,
Mipnei she-sakana hi lo, it's a סכנה sakana for him, so it's
not just the issue of
water of סתם stam medicinal treatments and the rabbinic problem. You can
even heat up water on שבת and even for the whole body.
Let's just finish this to the bottom. גופא, Gufa, אמר רב אין
מונעין חמין ושמן מעל גבי מכה בשבת. amar Rav ein monin chamin
v'shemen me-al gabei maka b'Shabbos. So this is again against this is
just the rabbinic problem of medicinal treatments on שבת. You do not
hold back hot water and oil from you can put it on
the wound, not a problem. Again תוספות Tosafot says it means mixed
together. If it's not mixed together, then it wouldn't even be an
obvious medicinal treatment. It's just you know putting water. around the wound
and then it can sort of
run into the wound. מיתבי *Meitvei* I'll ask you, there's אין נותנין
שמן וחמין על גבי מוך ליתן על גבי מכה בשבת *ein notnin
shemen v'chamin al gabei moch liten al gabei maka b'Shabbat*,
so this seems to be a proof for שמואל *Shmuel*, a proof
against רב *Rav*. It says you don't put oil and water on
a type of a cloth to put on the wound on שבת
*Shabbat*. You see you cannot directly apply it. שמואל'ס *Shmuel's* right. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says no, התם משום סחיטה *hatam mishum sechita*. That's
not a problem of medicinal. That's a problem that if it's on
a cloth, you'll come to squeeze out the cloth. Okay. תא שמע
*Ta shema*, come in here. אין נותנין חמין ושמן על גבי מוך
שעל גבי המכה בשבת *ein notnin chamin v'shemen al gabei moch she'al
gabei hamaka b'Shabbat*. Even if the cloth bandage was already there, you
don't put oil and water on the bandage that's on the wound
on שבת *Shabbat*. So the גמרא *Gemara* assumes that that wasn't about
squeezing because the bandage is already there, so there's not, you know,
it's already sort of attached to the wound, so there's not a
concern you'll squeeze. It must be the medicinal problem. But says no,
התם נמי משום סחיטה *hatam nami mishum sechita*. Even if it's already
on the body, the concern there is you'll squeeze it, but the
medicinal issue is not there. And if there's no bandage, you can
put it directly on the wound. תניא כוותיה דשמואל *Tanya k'vatei d'Shmuel*,
we taught like שמואל *Shmuel* that you cannot put it directly on
the wound, even without a bandage. אין נותנין חמין ושמן על גבי
מכה בשבת *ein notnin chamin v'shemen al gabei maka b'Shabbat*. You cannot
put it directly on the wound on שבת *Shabbat*, the oil and
water, אבל נותן חוץ למכה ושוטף ויורד למכה *aval noten chutz l'maka
v'shotef v'yored l'maka*. You can put it on and it runs into
it, exactly like שמואל *Shmuel* says. Last point about this. תנו רבנן
*Tanu rabbanan*. נותנים על גבי המכה מוך יבש וספוג יבש *notnin al
gabei hamaka moch yavesh u'sfog yavesh*. You can put a dry piece
of cloth or a dry sponge on it because that prevents it
from getting infected, you know, or for rubbing up against your garment.
It's more preventative but it's not curative. אבל לא גמי יבש *aval
lo gemi yavesh*, not a dried like piece of, like, you know,
like of rubber, ולא קטיטין יבשים *v'lo ktitin yaveshim*,
and not dried up pieces of cloth. Those were understood to actually
have some curative effect. So the גמרא *Gemara* says one minute. קשיא
קטיטין אקטיטין *kashya ktitin a'ktitin*. First you said you could put a
מוך *moch*, which is basically a piece of cloth, and then you
said you can't put on pieces of cloth. So make up your
mind. Can you or can't you? So says לא קשיא *lo kashya*,
it's not difficult. הא בחדתי הא בעתיקי *ha b'chadti ha b'atiki*. It's
different between new and old. New ones are curative, old ones are
just preventative. אמר אביי שמע מינה *Amar Abaye shema mina*, from this
you see הני קטיטין מסו *hanei ktitin masu*, that pieces of cloth
on a wound actually can have a curative effect. And therefore it
gets to this issue of doing medicinal treatments on שבת *Shabbat*.